- I want to use, well, I guess it's nice. - Yeah. - And then I have a way to do this. - I'm sorry, I'm just trying to catch it. - When you see them with the bruises, they smoke with this guy, you can go to my service. - I can't do this. - Well, you should try to do it. - Why not? - I'm a businessman.
Speaker 1: Good morning,
Speaker 2: buenos dias,
Speaker 3: dobra nutra.
Speaker 4: How is
Speaker 5: everyone here today? Good. Thanks for coming out. My name is Eric Swenson, I'm the mayor of Woodford and it's a pleasure
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): to welcome you all here to Pallor Middle School.
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): Just inside this gym, my wife, Alejandra Mandujano Clements, teaches PE every day. And my son went to the school, now at the high school. It's a pleasure to be here. I would like to start by introducing some of our elected officials. And so I'm going to start with Linda Reeves. She's the chair of the Woodburn School Board. Her husband is our superintendent.
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): Lynn was the superintendent of the North Merian School District and is now serving on our school board and a quick announcement just Thursday we hired Oscar Moreno Gilson to be Woodburn's next superintendent so we're feeling very good about that. He's an assistant superintendent currently in the public.
Also my good friend
Speaker 3: Nkwate, Este Roland Herrera, Kaiser City Councilor, Woodburn High School
graduate.
And before my
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): next introduction, you know you're all here to hear United States Senator Merkley, who began as a state representative in Oregon, and so I am very proud to present not only our current state representative, but if you can make the connection, people become state representatives
Speaker 7: and then United States senators. So please welcome Teresa Alonzo León, our state
representative.
and future
Speaker 5: United States Senator. I've already signed up for that campaign. I've already made my donation to that campaign.
During his
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): service as a state representative and as our United States Senator, Jeff Merkley has emphasized fighting for the success of Oregon's working families. That means fighting for good-paying jobs, strong public schools, and affordable college, and healthcare.
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): Just last year, he used his position on the Senate Appropriations Committee to secure more than $2 billion for affordable housing and homelessness services. He has also
taken a number of actions to help
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): the region's wine growers, including securing disaster relief for wine growers affected by wildfire smoke and funding research into the impacts of smoke on wine grapes so we can respond more
Speaker 8: effectively in the
future.
- You know
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): that Senator Merkley was considering to run for president, and I'm sure he would have the votes right here, and the way that stood out. I'm
also signing
Speaker 7: up for that campaign, if that happens
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): again. And particularly to Woodburn, I've been a middle school and high school principal here, and I've worked with all the hardworking families, and it was such a heartwarming experience for our residents,
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): during the heart-wrenching time when so many family members of even people in Woodburn were being detained in detention centers in Walmarts in Texas and to have our United States Senator stand in front of that Walmart and broadcast to the world what was happening you have the eternal great
Speaker 8: gratitude
of our community Senator
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): Merkley is a native Oregonian and the son of a millwright he was born in Myrtle Creek
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): And his family moved with the timber economy to Roseburg and then to East Multnomah County. He was elected to the Oregon House of Representatives in 1998. In 2007, he became Speaker of the Oregon House and held that position until he was elected to the United States Senator. He began his involvement in policy as a young intern for Oregon Senator Mark Hadfield.
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): In 2009, he was sworn in to the same sentence he once held by Senator Hadfield. Senator Berkley holds an open town hall in every Oregon county every year. This is his 22nd town hall this year, and his 418th
Speaker 8: overall. And we're very happy to have him. Please welcome your United States Senator, Jeff Franklin.
Speaker 9: well greetings everyone thank
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): you so much for coming out today we have a much smaller
Speaker 11: turnout than usual we normally completely fill this this room and so we'll have a bit of conversation about the coronavirus and that challenge that represents but before we do that let's turn to putting a spotlight
Speaker 11: something that has strengthened
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): our community and our state. I try to do that at every town hall and today I'm particularly pleased to shine a light on the role that Willamette Valley Vineyards has played and Jim Berno is here. Am I pronouncing it right? Come
Speaker 12: on up
Jim. Come on up.
So we had a
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): real challenge with the fires two summers ago, and
Speaker 11: those fires, the smoke from it affected the health around our state. It also affected many of our businesses. One business I met with was a furniture salesman, and their furniture, they had a real problem with getting the smoke smell out of the furniture.
Speaker 11: But think about how much of a challenge that is with wine grapes. And many of the virus, the significant virus, canceled their orders in the last moment, even when the grapes weren't tainted. And this is where Jim stepped in. And why don't I have you tell a story?
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): Thank you, Senator. You know, it's not hard for us to make our living, at least at some time in our lives, in agriculture.
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): imagine what happened in the Rogue Valley. Think about you growing your crop and putting all your savings and your money into growing that crop through the growing season only to learn just a few days before your harvest that your grapes were not going to be accepted by the
buyer. How are you
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): going to pay your mortgage?
How are you
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): going to make sure you have the money for next season?
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): That's the challenge that our growers faced. And they didn't have insurance. And so when they reached out to us as winemakers here in the Willamette Valley, we banded together as an industry to see if we could help them. And even Senator Murphy's staff came down to help us pick the grapes, to save some of the grapes, as many grapes
as we could.
And we as
Speaker 16: winemakers, and
Speaker 17: imagine this,
Speaker 16: imagine,
you
Speaker 17: know, think about winemakers, how strong they are, imagine
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): winemakers getting together to agree on making a wine together.
Speaker 18: It's like,
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): it's like having, you know, four chefs in your kitchen with all the sharp knives out on the
Speaker 19: counter. You know,
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): it's not easy to get those winemakers to agree on what to do, but we did something no one had ever done.
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): And that was to work together as winemakers to figure out how to make an Oregon Solidarity wine
as a
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): fundraiser for the damaged Rogue Valley growers with the net proceeds going back to those growers. So we paid for the grapes in cash so they'd have the money for their mortgages and then we covered with the net proceeds money to support the Rogue Valley vendors.
Speaker 17: Anyway.
Speaker 17: i want to thank senator because he then not only followed through on helping
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): those growers with the disaster relief that they needed but also with the research that we needed i mean these fires are a serious matter there is smoke tape when in the particular case frankly a very large california winery uses as an excuse to back out of those uh the great picks that's really what happened we made over 7 500 cases of orange and solidary wine we still have some left
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): So you can get some of this delicious wine made by the wine makers here in the Willamette Valley. It's been a privilege to work with you, Senator, and your staff. And it's an example of the values that we all hold dear, and we've got each other's back. So thank you.
I think the Chardonnay is
Speaker 21: sold out.
Speaker 11: And you had a rosé, I think, as well, that's gone. So what's the... Pinot Noir. It's still
Speaker 22: available. And can people get that online? Yes, and
Speaker 17: there's a number of stores that sell this line. Roth sells it, Safeway sells it, Fred Meyer. You'll find this in a number of locations. And you can call us. It's delicious.
Speaker 17: So just as a way
Speaker 23: of recognizing
Speaker 9: and celebrating this
Speaker 11: work, and I just even just wrote the works, Oregon Solidarity, this time where there's so many divisive forces coming together as a community to solve a challenge. It's just a beautiful thing. So to recognize that,
Speaker 24 (lower-pitched voice): this is a flag.
Speaker 24 (lower-pitched voice): for you to use an appropriate fashion that has been flown over the U.S. Capitol. Thank you very much.
How is the wine
Speaker 26: labeled?
Speaker 25: It's
Speaker 17: labeled Oregon Solidarity and has the signatures of the winemakers on the back label. I failed to mention one other thing. Our industry has a Nobel Prize, essentially, that
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): is awarded in our industry And--
Speaker 15 (lower-pitched voice): This wine, this project, was recognized by our industry receiving the Wine Star Award for Innovation.
So much
Speaker 11: going on.
Speaker 11: But let's start by talking about the challenge we're facing with the coronavirus. We do have a couple of health care experts here who can answer more detailed questions as they come up in the town hall, but I just wanted to give you some general sense. We are, by the way, we're Facebook-ing this, if I stay in the right spot, so people can participate without coming to a town hall if they felt uncomfortable doing so.
Speaker 11: What we're facing, you might think of it a little bit like the equivalent of a scary flu season. And we're in person-to-person contact, the disease moves, and it moves through people coughing or sneezing and you proceed to have it on your hands from a handrail or who knows what. And you put your hand to your nose or your mouth and then you get infected.
Speaker 11: uh so that's why there's so much emphasis right now on really trying to affect transmission which is why i'm trying to be disciplined you saw i just forgot just now i almost shook hands with jim and he reminded me uh so it really helps to wash your hands
Speaker 11: to use hand sanitizer, to consciously try not to put your hands to your face, and those things interrupt the infections. We do have several new cases in Oregon that we just announced this morning. We had three cases, now I think we have a total of seven. And some of those are from travel, and one is from person-to-person contact. We'll learn more about them. We are seeing the numbers go up very rapidly, and that's very scary.
Speaker 11: We had a briefing on Thursday morning with the Secretary Azar and the top health professionals. And at that briefing, they said, "Well, we now have 120 identified cases." Well, here we are on Saturday morning, two days later, we have more than 300 identified cases. If you went back seven days ago, we had 26 identified cases, so 26, 120, 300.
Speaker 11: Now, a good part of that is that test kits are being now moved throughout the country to try to get test kits everywhere. So we're testing people we weren't testing before. So it doesn't mean this disease is moving that fast, it probably means the test kits are getting distributed and we're testing more people. Most people who are younger with healthy immune systems will see very mild symptoms.
Speaker 11: It's the disease is the sort of thing that attacks people who have particular health care challenges with the immune system or lung issues or are older and more frail and fragile. So in that sense it's kind of similar to the way the flu is. Now the flu, think about the flu. Since 2010 we've had bad flu seasons and light flu seasons. In a light flu season, 14,000 Americans died from the flu.
Speaker 11: That's a significant number. In a heavy flu season, more than 60,000 die. We don't know how this will be proportional to that. I asked on Thursday morning, what is our best guess on the lethality of this disease? And one expert gave one answer, and then another expert set up and said, no, no, no, that's not right at all. That doesn't take into account all the people who are infected who have mild symptoms. And he thought that the lethality best guess would be equivalent to flu, or perhaps up to 10 times worse.
Speaker 11: That's still significant, variation, so we don't know, but the point is we're trying to break the chain of communication or of flu from one person or the coronavirus from one person to another in, as they may be very thoughtful about our hands, it comes down to our hands. So, that's that.
Speaker 11: There are so many other issues around the nation, I'll just mention a few of them. We have the challenge of investments in the foundations for families to thrive, issues related to
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): health care, to housing, to education, to living wage jobs. We have the challenge
Speaker 11: of really erosion of the credibility of our institutions and our election system, gerrymandering.
Speaker 11: voter suppression and intimidation breaking out in all kinds of ways, and then dark money in campaigns that has been unleashed by the Citizens United decision a few years ago. There is a bill to take this on called the For the People Act. Senator Udall from New Mexico and I are the leads of this in the Senate. We have 47 co-sponsors. We'd like to have 100 co-sponsors protecting the integrity of our election system.
Speaker 11: This bill, by the way, has passed the House. It was in the House known as H.R.1. So if you've heard of H.R.1, it's for the people out there. We have certainly the challenge of carbon pollution and trying to take on the challenges. We see so many challenges of that in Oregon. I'll address that more if people raise the issue. But it's very important that we quickly move towards a renewable energy economy.
Speaker 11: So those are just a few of the issues. I really want to leave this time for you all to raise what's on your mind. I think the mayor has agreed to mix up all those tickets that you got on the way in, make sure everybody has an
Speaker 29: equal chance of asking a question or making a point. If someone's making a point
Speaker 30: that you
Speaker 31: completely, passionately disagree
with,
Speaker 30: please be dumbly respectful of that individual. Let them have their say. Now, the
Speaker 11: tradition of town halls is disappearing across America.
Speaker 11: But here with the Oregon way of listening to each other, we've maintained it. In fact, I think it's thriving in our state. Both Senator Wyden and I go to a town hall in every county every year, plus a whole lot of other public panels and so forth in addition. And that in the friction that we have in our nation, kind of the tribal frictions that may be between parties or between urban and rural,
Speaker 11: Other folks across the country have given up on the town halls. Let's double down on the communication in town halls and listening to each other and respecting each other in the different positions that might be shared. So with that, let's turn to tickets, and these tickets,
Speaker 30: these white tickets, they almost all start with 590. I think they all start with 590.
Speaker 30: So, I am not going to read the first three numbers, 'cause you get all excited. Oh, five, five, four, that's fine. No. I'll just read the last three numbers on the right. And just raise your hand, and then we'll ask you to tell us your number and your name. 222, 226, and 236. Just raise your hand if you have any of those. Yes, right up here. We'll get you started, and then right here. This is the front row. Okay, we'll come to you next.
Speaker 30: And tell us your name and your number, please.
Speaker 32: I'm Martin Sanders, 2-2-2. I grew up in Mount Angel. Three
Speaker 33: miles in there. Play ball, right over here at St. Luke's. Anyway, what I want
Speaker 34: to ask about is the war,
Speaker 33: Senator. We are
Speaker 35 (higher-pitched voice): bombing eight countries
this morning. We
Speaker 35 (higher-pitched voice): have siege warfare
with eight-- I think it's eight countries.
That's more than half of the discretionary budget is spent
Speaker 35 (higher-pitched voice): on these foreign wars. We have Tulsi Gabbard will be on Oregon's ballot. She's the first anti-war candidate we've had since Robert Kennedy in 1968. Why don't you guys ever talk about the damn war? We have Trump has dropped an average of 44,000 bombs a year for three years.
Now, I
Speaker 35 (higher-pitched voice): think you guys are going to talk about it, because Obama dropped 20,000 bombs a year
for eight
Speaker 35 (higher-pitched voice): years, and he won a Nobel Peace Prize
for doing it.
Speaker 35 (higher-pitched voice): So what in the hell is going on? Why don't we talk about where we're spending
Speaker 36: most of our money?
Thank
Speaker 11: you. Thank you, and I see you have some Tulsi handouts there, if anyone would
Speaker 30: like to get more information in your pocket.
Speaker 30: I think this is a really big issue, and let me touch on a couple pieces of it. The first is that I think we
Speaker 11: made some really big mistakes in our strategy. With Afghanistan, I think we should have destroyed the training centers where people were being trained to be terrorists, but we shouldn't have tried to occupy the country and turn it into a Western democracy.
Speaker 11: we've lost thousands of lives a trillion dollars huge number of injuries that will haunt american soldiers for the rest of their their their lifetimes and we've really that occupation hasn't produced anything that looks like a western democracy nor was that really possible i think about one of richard um not richard kipling's uh poems about the british soldier
Speaker 11: being rejected by the tribes in Afghanistan. And it ends with kind of a graphic paragraph that speaks to the fact that the soldiers were not, well, the great soldiers were not well accepted. And would you like to hear that? - Yeah, no, I am. - Okay, like I said, it's pretty bad. Let's see if I can remember it.
Speaker 11: If you find yourself wounded on the Afghanistan plane, roll over on your rifle and blow out your braids before the women come out and carve up what remains. So pretty graphic. Every group that has gone into Afghanistan has left, not changed the basic tribal character. In Iraq, the non-existent weapons of mass destruction that we went in,
Speaker 11: Iraq was a very stable counterpart to Iran, a vicious dictator for sure, but we went under false pretenses and we created chaos that is now haunting us, and it's also thousands of lives lost, trillions of dollars, or trillion dollars lost, and many, many injuries.
Speaker 11: This shows one thing that I think we need to emphasize, which is any decision to go to war needs to abide with our Constitution, which says that decision is too big an issue to be made by a single person in the Oval Office. That it needs to come to Congress, and there has to be an authorization by Congress, and then that authorization needs to be followed.
Speaker 11: now the afghanistan authorization it did come from congress but it was very narrow it said those who attacked us on 9-11 and those who harbor those who attacked us that has been stretched now to justify action in well a lot of nations i think it's actually more than eight and then we have the 2002 for iraq and it was very very narrow and precise
Speaker 11: uh regarding uh that particular uh situation with the relieved weapons of mass destruction and that's now being used by administration to say that would justify war in iran and so i put forward a provision with others that said mr president no these authorizations do not justify war in iran you have to come to congress to get authorization uh that's what the constitution says and we need to follow the Constitution.
Well, in terms of our military
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): budget, I spent a couple of years working for Secretary Weinberger. And there's massive
Speaker 11: waste in our military budget. And quite frankly, we're falling behind other nations, other developed nations, on our infrastructure, on our education, on our investment in housing, which we see a big impact on. And I do think we need to move billions and billions of dollars from the defense enterprise,
Speaker 11: and
Speaker 29: cut out a lot of that to waste and duplication and move it into health
Speaker 24 (lower-pitched voice): care and housing and education and infrastructure.
Did we have 226 or
Speaker 37: 236? Yes, right up here.
- I just wanted to know. - Your number and name, please. - 226.
I'm
Speaker 39: from Mount Angel,
and my name
Speaker 39: is Pat, and I just wanted to know, all the things that Trump has done, all the turnovers, the clean
Speaker 40: water, the drain works, the forestry, and
what
Speaker 40: the virus and everything else, and he's put in all this money for our budget.
Does he get to keep all that or is somebody able to turn
Speaker 41: over our Clean Water Act and our DreamWorkers and our Immigration?
Speaker 41: This is a very, very broad question you're asking.
Speaker 11: It's touched on pretty much everything. Let me just take one piece of it philosophically, which is the president cannot operate outside the laws established by Congress, because there's a lot of room for flexibility in regulation.
Speaker 11: And then the strategy and vision in the constitutional system of checks and balances that Congress can obtain witnesses and documents to be able to say, "Okay, is what you're doing in accordance with law or not?" That check and balance is now in dire concern. There is a case called McGann case where Congress has to do the subpoena.
Speaker 11: And the lower court has said, you can't subpoena the executive branch. Well, if you can't get documents and witnesses, you can't do oversight. And it would just absolutely gut the accountability to law that the Constitution envisions.
Speaker 11: Their founders were very, very concerned about
Speaker 30: presidents kind of thinking back to the pre-colonial kingdoms in Europe and, well, the law wouldn't have a president tempted to
Speaker 11: be a king. The whole way to prevent that was to have congressional oversight to keep people within the law, so I'm very concerned about the erosion of that.
Speaker 11: And so I'm going to use that as a way to try to answer your question that we have to, hopefully we'll see this is going to be appealed to the Supreme Court, or it has been appealed, I'm certainly hoping that congressional oversight is sustained by the Supreme Court, because if there's anything that's core to the Constitution, it's this check and balance. If we lose this case,
Speaker 11: then we're really in the world of an imperial presidency, which is not at all what the founders
Speaker 24 (lower-pitched voice): or our constitution envisions. And then we're in real trouble. They were in real trouble now.
Speaker 11: We're in more trouble than-- thank you. And did we have the final one, 2-3-6? Yes. I'm
going to read on deck
Speaker 11: 224, 2-2-1, and 2-4-1. So if you have any of those, we'll
Speaker 42: get to you in a moment.
Speaker 42: So, 2-3-6, I'm Michael Sanchez, the president
Speaker 43 (lower-pitched voice): of Chemecto Students for Life and the Oregon State Captain for Students for Life Action. Last week, we voted against closure on the motion to proceed with the Born and Alive Abortion Survivors Protection Act. This legislation would have effectively criminalized infanticide nationwide, required abortionists to provide life-saving care to babies born alive, and ensure surviving infants get admitted to a hospital.
Speaker 43 (lower-pitched voice): Can you please explain your vote and tell us what is currently happening to those babies who are being born alive after a failed abortion? - So
Speaker 30: this, we already have lost kids and fantasize. This bill was put
Speaker 11: forward as a campaign strategy and it goes to the heart of whether Uncle Sam is the right force to be making healthcare decisions with a doctor and a woman.
Speaker 11: And I believe that you have very challenging situations that come about in a later term abortion. You have an individual who wanted to carry a baby to term but then terrible things develop in the health of the baby or the health of the mother.
Speaker 11: Those are extraordinarily challenging, and I think the right way to resolve them is between a woman, her partner, her religious advisor, minister, and her doctor. And that the federal government is absolutely not the right presence to insert into the exam room, and that's why I voted against that bill.
So can you
Speaker 44: answer my second question as well about what's happening to Vegas born alive after an abortion? I'll
Speaker 11: leave that to healthcare experts to take that one off. 241,
Speaker 45: 221, and 224.
Speaker 46: Hello,
I'm sorry.
Speaker 46: First off, I really love the job you've
Speaker 47: done. You're really awesome. You need more seconds like me. I really
Speaker 48: do sincerely appreciate what you've done.
Speaker 49 (lower-pitched voice): My question is about the 2005 bankruptcy bill that-- I hate to say it, but the joke I am, kind of ran through with-- and then it was signed into law by Bush and all the Republicans. You're familiar. I don't know any of you familiar with it.
Speaker 49 (lower-pitched voice): The law that outlawed discharges private student loan debt for the first time in the history of our country, right? My wife, my daughter, and I collectively have $500,000 in student loan debt. You heard that right, half a billion
Speaker 50 (lower-pitched voice): dollars. Wells Fargo and Bank of America and KeyBank are never going to get that money. They could hold a gun to my head.
Speaker 50 (lower-pitched voice): and it wouldn't make a damn bit of difference. I'm going to work until I drop dead
Speaker 49 (lower-pitched voice): and they can dig up my corpse from the grave. Take my rings off and see what they can sell them all for. Like, go ahead. Take my teeth out. I'm being serious now. Now that it looks like the erasure
Speaker 50 (lower-pitched voice): of student love that is probably not going to happen because of current events, you know, in the primary.
Speaker 50 (lower-pitched voice): Would you please, please, please, please work to overturn that law? Please. I'm not the only one.
I'm part of it.
Speaker 49 (lower-pitched voice): There's millions of people just like me, and it has killed my daughter's life. Me and my wife are going to go. We're both over 60 now. This is our life. Can you help out, please?
How many folks have
Speaker 52: student loan debt?
How many of
Speaker 30: you have family members who are concerned about student loan debt?
Speaker 30: Quite a lot. It's a very big
Speaker 11: deal. You know, when I got out of high school, if you worked minimum wage for the summer and you lived in a home made out of the fridge, you could pay tuition at an Oregon Public University. Try doing that today. We're in a whole different world.
And yet,
Speaker 11: the economy has more and more pathways that demand a college education. We should promote every pathway to success in terms of training and the skills, the apprenticeship programs, all of the trades that don't require college, but many require college. And so other countries are invested in education
Speaker 11: so that their citizens do not have college loan debt. They aren't all free, although in Germany, tuition is pretty close to free. And
Speaker 30: so I think we have to at least move to a debt-free opportunity at our public universities. We have
Speaker 11: now, in Oregon, for folks coming out of high school, created the AAB. And I salute our state
Speaker 30: legislators for doing this.
Speaker 30: They've created a pathway to a--
Speaker 11: Mojanin to Teresa. And they've created a pathway on a high school to go to where I think it costs $50 of credit in your first two years at a community college. That's a great step forward. But we really-- it makes no sense at all to have people view higher education as going to produce debt the size of a home mortgage
Speaker 11: that's going to constrain you your entire life. And I live in a blue-collar community on the outskirts of Portland. That community, people tell me I'm not sure I should encourage my kids to go to college because they may end up with this type of death. That is not an aspirational
Speaker 11: Opportunity for all society. We talk about the American dream and the
Speaker 30: vision that everyone has an opportunity to thrive and do well, but to do that, you have to have a well-paved road for people to travel. Now,
there's an American...
Speaker 30: a journalist who comes from Oregon, Nicholas Kristof. And he's just written a book called Tightrope. And it's about how that road has become so narrow and jagged, it's more like trying to walk a tightrope, and you
Speaker 11: fall off. And he documents how his community of Anhill, Oregon, has seen this in spades. So for everyone who has debt, I think they should be able to refinance that 6%, 8%, 10%
debt
Speaker 11: to the same rate the
Speaker 30: big banks get, when they borrow from the federal government, which is like 1%. We
Speaker 53: need
to vastly increase
Speaker 54: the Pell grants.
Speaker 29: And then we need to enable there to be enough financial aid so that people can go to a public university
Speaker 11: equivalent debt-free. So they can thrive in their lives. They can buy houses, which people can't do
Speaker 30: now because that debt hangs over. You know, home ownership,
Speaker 30: took a really bad hit in 2008-2009 because of the predatory mortgages. I took on the task of getting rid of those mortgages when I went to the U.S. Senate, succeeded. I passed the bill in the Oregon House when I was Speaker to get rid of those predatory mortgages. The Oregon Senate didn't act, but when I went to the Senate,
I started
Speaker 30: Talking about this and Senator Dodd said, come to the banking committee. I want to put you in the banking committee. Leave this charge. Get rid of these predatory mortgages. And I did. So we don't have those triple options. We don't have those negative advertising. We don't have those exploding interest rate mortgages anymore. But what we do have is student debt. That means people can't qualify for mortgages. And we also have prices so high that you can't afford to buy them.
Speaker 54: but they are the major driver of middle class wealth. So
Speaker 30: instead of having $500,000 in student debt, it'd be great to have $500,000 in equity. That puts you in a whole different position. And that's the type of change we have to make here in the United States of America.
Which number do we have? 224. Thank
Speaker 55: you. We have 221 and 241.
Hello,
Speaker 56: Senator. I have
Speaker 57 (lower-pitched voice): 241. My name is George New Year. I'm out of London. I'd like to ask you a little bit more regarding checks and balances. Between our three branches, those checks and balances have had
a lot of
Speaker 57 (lower-pitched voice): tradition and norm based into keeping them upright. What statute would you like to
see?
Speaker 57 (lower-pitched voice): Added to it. Maybe you could talk a little bit about what's an HR1 or any any traditions or norms that you think aren't cutting
it.
Speaker 29: Okay, well thank you for the invitation to talk about the HR1, the Poor the People Act. So
Speaker 30: here is something to ponder.
If you
Speaker 30: look at the distribution of wealth in America, we're back in the Gilded Age.
Speaker 30: Huge concentration at the top. Over the last four decades, our national wealth has grown enormously, but not for working people. Working people incomes have been flat or declining. That wealth at the top becomes very powerful and can overwhelm the machinery of a democratic republic. By that I mean the most powerful individuals can have huge panels of lawyers who litigate everything and push everything.
Speaker 30: They can hire lobbyists. The drug industry has-- I haven't fact-checked this, so I say that out loud because I keep meaning to do so. So I'll register for my team-- that there are five drug lobbyists for every member of Congress. And then you have the money in the campaigns. And then you have the money in the media campaigns. And then you have the money behind the social media campaigns. And then you have the money that goes to the ownership of media. So all of this--
Speaker 30: can result in a tipping point where even despite the machinery of elections, the powerful make laws to make the rich richer. And we saw this in 2017 with a tax bill that gave $2 trillion away almost entirely to the richest Americans.
What
Speaker 30: would happen if we get those $2 trillion back and invested in housing, and healthcare, and education, and infrastructure here in the United States
and America? So we have to take on the things that have happened that have twisted the machinery
Speaker 30: of government. One is gerrymandering. So the bill or the people bill would say there have to be independent commissions
Speaker 11: across the land.
Speaker 11: And those that work pretty well, for example, in Pennsylvania to take a highly gerrymandered state and make
Speaker 30: it reflect the distribution of viewpoints in that state. A second is the essentially restoring the Voting Rights Act and utilizing the experiences we have from Oregon so that we guarantee automatic voter registration, early voting, paper
Speaker 58: ballots that can be recounted
by voting voters.
It would stop
Speaker 59: polling place manipulation,
Speaker 30: so you had to have staffing equivalent at each polling station according to the population of that precinct, so you couldn't have short lines in precincts you favor, politically, and six-hour lines in ones you don't. It takes on all those issues, and I think Oregon is the national leader in this. If we could just copy the Oregon system, it would stop a huge amount of voter intimidation
Speaker 30: and manipulation, including stopping the purging of voting rolls in a partisan fashion, which happened in Georgia and other states. And it's completely biasing the outcome of elections. So that's the second. The third big one is the money and how it flows. There's so much dark money, hundreds of millions of dollars flowing through these campaigns.
Speaker 30: You see these ads by groups like Generation Opportunity and so forth that you don't know who's behind. You don't know. You can't track the money. It's like a shell game. It goes from this to this to this to this to this. You can't tell what the original donors were. And if you could, you couldn't track where their money ended up. And so it takes on. It shines a light and gets rid of the shell game strategy of hiding the path of money.
Speaker 30: We can't actually overturn Citizens United, which says unlimited sums by billionaires into campaigns. But we can, in fact, shine a light so
Speaker 11: we can see where every dime comes from. So that would be a huge improvement. And then it has an ethics section to reduce the conflicts of interest. And so I think passing that, I'd like to see that passed in January 2021. And I hope it gets 100 votes in the U.S. Senate.
And it raises an issue about
Speaker 23: the Senate because
Speaker 54: of the fact that the
Speaker 11: lobby absolutely does not want that to pass. They have tremendous power the way things are.
Speaker 11: And one of those powers is the supermajority in the Senate. I've watched the Senate lose two key items over my working lifetime from the time I was first entering for Senator Hatfield and working for Congress in the '80s. And one of those was the ability to put any issue on the floor as a senator. So you could force the debate and the vote.
Speaker 11: on all kinds of things that make powerful lobbies uncomfortable because they don't want that debated they don't want to vote it that's gone there were virtually no amendments last year and virtually no bills last year uh the uh the second is that the senate has for our history been a simple majority in virtually all circumstances as the founders envisioned and it's become now a super majority that gives tremendous power to the lobby to stop things when they need a smaller number of people to vote against against uh taking on it's why we haven't And I'm taking my background.
Speaker 11: That's why we haven't taken on the high cost of drugs, is in part the supermajority in the Senate. Hamilton said, don't do this. And he used language like, you will see by this being supermajority, tedious delays and contemptuous compromises of the common good.
Speaker 30: Madison said, do not let the will of the majority be bent to the will of the minority. It undermines the very premise of our democratic republic.
Speaker 30: So we have now made the very mistake the founders warn us against, we have to correct that mistake and
Speaker 29: return the Senate to being a legislative body that can debate and can vote and can address the problems we see all
Speaker 61: across America.
Speaker 62: 229, 235, 219.
And if
Speaker 30: none, we will go quickly. Yes, thank you. My
name is Barbara
Speaker 63: Winn.
Speaker 64: 219 is my name. 219, thank you. My question is, of the hundreds of bills that the Senate majority party were not allowed to be voted on that have come to the Senate from the House, name some other priority bills besides the ones you've already talked about.
Speaker 30: Well, these 350 bills, they cover the spectrum. But let me
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): shine a light on a couple that we haven't talked about. One is the Equality Act. The
Speaker 11: Equality Act comes out of Oregon.
Speaker 11: When I was speaker here at Oregon, we passed the Equality Act that said we're going to use the foundation of the 64 Civil Rights Act and we're going to say that every person has an opportunity to employment, to jury duty, to mortgages as everyone else. No more door slamming because people...
Speaker 11: are LGBT individuals. Everyone gets to participate in our society. So that bill, we passed in Oregon, and then Ted Kennedy asked me to lead the battle for the Employment Non-Discrimination Act 'cause he was sick and dying of cancer. I led that battle, we passed that bill in the Senate. The House didn't take it up, and it died. And then I worked with others to take the Oregon Equality Act and create the National Equality Act, which has now passed the House of Representatives,
Speaker 11: And it has not been taken up in the Senate. Isn't it time we ended discrimination across our country against the LGBTQ community? And
the
Speaker 65: climate, carbon
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): bills, bills to facilitate
Speaker 10 (lower-pitched voice): the transition to renewable
Speaker 11: energy, then there's a host of those that have died. We have massive subsidies to the fossil fuel industry. I'll tell you, so I guess it was two years ago, there was a bill to fill research into wind energy because Senator from Tennessee really hates wind turbines. And so I talked to
a friend of mine,
Speaker 11: a senator from Grassford, from Iowa, there's a lot of wind there. And I said, would you partner with me? We'll have a bipartisan stand for research into renewable wind energy. And he said, absolutely. So we go to the floor, and Senator Lamar Alexander from Tennessee stands up and says, we don't need this because this is a mature
Speaker 30: industry, and why shouldn't we subsidize research on the mature industry? And I stood up and
Speaker 11: said, well, first of all, wind technology is changing dramatically.
Speaker 11: different now than five years ago if we do research it'll be very different five years forward there's all kinds of new potential and so this is where research is needed meanwhile if we want
Speaker 30: to cancel subsidies into a mature industry how about canceling subsidies into a 150 year old industry called the fossil
fuel industry
Speaker 30: so
Speaker 11: score one for but there's so many bills that have died in that sector okay we have two two nine and two three
five yes two
Speaker 66: three five
thanks
Senator
Speaker 67: Rickley, I come to you as a Quicken woman, we have over 1100 tribal members here
in the Portland
Speaker 67: metro area and Alaska. I come to you regarding the VAWA Bill, the United States Women's Act Bill, and how they're trying to reclassify what's
being
Speaker 67: domestic violence and stuff that's going on. And understanding that we're strong in the sector out of Alaska to find some of the issues. So I wanted to know what's happening, especially with the senator out of Ohio who's wanting to rewrite it, we classify
Speaker 68: everything. Under the current executive administration, it would put a lot of us out there.
Speaker 11: Yeah, so the last renewal of this Violence Against Women Act, we took on
Speaker 30: two big issues, violence against tribal women and domestic violence and stalking. And we're now trying to renew it again because it's, I think it was a five-year bill, the five years have passed, and it's being blocked by the Senate leadership.
Speaker 30: so I don't have a lot more details for you we're so appreciative of Senator Murkowski's leadership but we don't have a critical
Speaker 11: mass when I said almost no bills have been on the floor this is really an example like shouldn't we at least debate it shouldn't we
Speaker 30: at least have to vote on it and we have to be accountable to our voters for where we stand on it none of that happens if it doesn't come to the floor of the Senate so I think we would win if it came to the floor of the Senate
but
So
Speaker 30: think about this structural problem. The Senate was designed with no constitutional leader, except presiding vice president, who in practice doesn't actually preside, had no power over the rules. The idea was distributed power among the 100. But under the recent changes in the abuse of the privilege of the majority, you're not a constitutional position, leader of the majority party in the Senate,
Speaker 30: takes the privilege to be the first called on for an amendment or the first called on for a motion to completely blockade bills from coming to the floor or from amendments to come to the floor. That is not distributed power among 100. That is a concentration of power that is absolutely destroying the Senate as a legislative body. One can agree or disagree with the work of the Oregon House, but I can tell you you can go down when all the members attend, and they will proceed.
Speaker 30: to debate on the floor 5 to 15 bills in an afternoon evening. Is that an exaggeration? Am I exaggerating?
A tiny bit.
Speaker 69: A tiny
Speaker 30: bit? What's the most bills in your experience that you've debated and voted on in an afternoon and evening?
-
Speaker 70 (higher-pitched voice): Well, it really depends on the size of the bill, right? - It does. - And if we decide to read the bill, so--
Speaker 71: - Okay, well, there's another delay tactic of reading every word, right?
Speaker 70 (higher-pitched voice): - Yeah, exactly, so they vary. So we may have, be able to go through, in some days we can go through five,
Speaker 70 (higher-pitched voice): Some days we can go through, you're right, maybe 10 or 15.
Speaker 72: - Thank you very
Speaker 30: much.
Speaker 70 (higher-pitched voice): - Nothing here about it,
yes. No, you're right, nothing here about
Speaker 30: it. - You used to go to the floor with all these bill folders and you're reading each one and then you're reading the next one and you're trying to
Speaker 11: catch up on who says what and what issue, and people change their opinions 'cause they're on the floor. You have to be within 30 seconds of the floor in order to vote. And so people go, oh, well that's a good point, I had to consider that.
Speaker 11: And there's a possibility of doing a minority report, which is a formative amendment on the floor. In fact, I was coming through the floor the other, about a week and a half ago, I think it was, and there was a minority report that won and modified the bill.
Speaker 11: I know that that's pretty rare, but it happened while I happened to be there. But you do not see anything like that in the Senate.
Speaker 30: Those words that used to describe the US Senate, the world's greatest deliberative body, it is now like the world's least deliberative legislative body. When I wrestle with
Speaker 11: running for re-election,
I felt the
Speaker 11: only way I'm running for re-election is if I just fight like hell to try to restore the Senate to being a legislative body where
Speaker 30: people's bills and amendments can be on the floor, we can vote, we can be held accountable for the people of the United States
of America. 220, 234,
Speaker 73: 228.
Speaker 74: - 220, my name is Steve
Speaker 75: Winn, I live in Kaiser.
- Who
Speaker 76 (lower-pitched voice): are you at next? - 220, my name is Steve Winn, I live in Kaiser, while I grew up and worked through high school. I guess my question is a little bit closer to home, where you see a lot of foreign land, there's some really excellent foreign land in this area, just on the other side of the railroad tracks on the left. There's a subdivision of some of the best foreign land in the world now.
Speaker 76 (lower-pitched voice): I'm wondering what we can do to protect farmland from development. Once developed, it rarely goes back to any of the use.
Speaker 30: Could you all catch that? What were we doing to protect farmland from development? So it's very interesting that you should raise this question.
Speaker 30: because Oregon has probably the strongest law in the nation to protect farmland in terms of our urban growth boundaries. I'm suspecting this must be land that was brought into the urban growth boundary. Is that-- you're not sure? I just know that just on the other side of the railroad tracks. OK. So--
Speaker 30: Going back to Tom McCall, Tom McCall said we don't want to become overrun with development and sprawl like California, so we'll create an urban growth boundary, kind of a virtual wall around each city, and those who have land outside that wall will get a special low tax rate, and that's forest and farmland, but they won't be able to put developments on it.
Speaker 30: those inside the urban growth boundary as long as they're still
Speaker 11: farming it and keeping it as farmland we'll still keep that low tax rate until they decide to sell it for for development so that has
Speaker 30: really constrained sprawl in Oregon and protected farmland and forestland compared to other states I don't know that particular piece of land but I'm guessing mayor do
Speaker 29: you know the answer do you want to tackle that no okay put you on the
Speaker 77: spot
Speaker 77: Thank you so much about that particular piece of property. It's just the idea in general. Well,
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): in general, so we had an initiative that was very misleading, and it destroyed our urban
Speaker 30: growth boundary strategy, and when I was speaker in 2007, we worked to craft
a
Speaker 30: And an initiative to go back to the people for a referral to say, do we want to save our land use system with the virtual wall and the protection of forest and farmland? And we won that pretty
Speaker 11: overwhelmingly at the ballot place. So it's still in place, if it's outside the urban growth boundary, it can't be developed, it has to stay as farmland or forest land that's inside.
Speaker 11: It could be developed, but there's an incentive to keep it in farmland as long as the owner wants to keep farming because they keep that low tax rate as if they were outside.
Speaker 30: So that's the basic answer. When people come to Oregon from states, all over the country, they come to study our urban growth system. And when you drive out of the urban growth boundary and suddenly the housing just stops, they go, well, how did that happen? Well, it's because of this being in place.
Speaker 29: Well, I'm told we're out
Speaker 30: of time.
Speaker 30: I know
Speaker 29: I have read two more numbers, and so I hate to cut off anyone after I've read the numbers, and if you know those
Speaker 30: two numbers, don't we want to speak quickly? 228. 228,
Speaker 78: okay. And we have 228 and 2934. So be very brief, and I'll try to be very brief. I will. Do you support the use of Superdellia's support to determine the next Democratic nomination?
Speaker 78: Question
Speaker 30: is in the Democratic convention, the use of superdelegates. I supported taking away the voting power of superdelegates in the first round. Nobody thought it would ever get to the second round, I don't think it will. And so I weigh in to take away the superdelegates vote in the first round. For both round or one? For the first round. And
Speaker 11: it's
very unlikely
Speaker 11: we'll ever get to a second.
Speaker 11: Well this time people think maybe, but if you look at the numbers now, the Democratic side is down to two viable candidates, it's almost impossible
Speaker 30: that it would go to a second round. Then may I ask you a follow-up question? Well, as long as it's not too political,
Speaker 78: because it's a bipartisan community gathering, but go ahead. Would you support Joe Biden, should he be the Democratic nominee? Yeah, that's too
Speaker 79: political.
Speaker 29: It's obvious that I've said this many times publicly
Speaker 11: in this context, and I apologize to our Republicans who are here, it's more of a party question than a community question, but I'm a Democrat and I'll react to whoever our nominee is, but I don't want to get more into the Democratic-Republican side of this in this setting.
Speaker 11: and and I know it was over you had the last one okay yes
Speaker 80: I'm 227 and I have a question about the detainees about those you
Speaker 81: have a number that was not called right yes I
have a question about the detainees that
Speaker 82 (higher-pitched voice): are crammed together
you know
Speaker 82 (higher-pitched voice): to a cell that's supposed to hold 12, that are sleeping on cold concrete, that are getting frozen burritos. How many of them have coronavirus that we're not being told about? How many are ill and how many have died that they are covering up? That's what
I want to know.
Speaker 30: I haven't heard of any
Speaker 11: reports of coronavirus among you speaking of refugees.
Speaker 11: uh there's almost no cases reported in mexico so
Speaker 24 (lower-pitched voice): far there are far more in canada uh than in mexico so that's the best information i have on it at this point uh where
Speaker 11: we have people concentrated together though like with flu uh if there is a case it would spread very easily very very quickly and we have to absolutely be on
Speaker 24 (lower-pitched voice): guard in old folks homes and prisons in any sort of setting where people
are jammed
Speaker 24 (lower-pitched voice): So I'll
Speaker 29: just close by thanking you all for coming out, and to those, I don't know how many are out there on Facebook, but if you're out there and actually are watching on Facebook, thank you for attending that session. We all are going to see a change. People are...
Speaker 29: There's a convention next weekend in Austin, Texas that was just canceled. There's going to be other things that are canceled with people a little concerned about coming out into public. So thank you all for saying this matters. I wanted to be here. You are here. I want to really thank our representative for her work and for our mayor, for MC, much appreciated. I am looking at the flag at the other end. United, we stand.
Speaker 29: How about we have
Speaker 30: a little less division, maybe a lot less division, and a lot more in the sense that we're coming together as Americans to build a more successful,
Speaker 11: a more beautiful, and a more prosperous nation together. Thank you.